{"test_questions": [[{"question": "Water contains", "opta": "one hydrogen atom and one oxygen atom", "optb": "two hydrogen atoms and one oxygen atom", "optc": "one hydrogen atom and two oxygen atoms", "optd": "three hydrogen atoms and two oxygen atoms", "opte": "two hydrogen atoms and three oxygen atoms.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Unit Hydrograph theory was enunciated by", "opta": "Merril Bernard", "optb": "W.W. Horner", "optc": "Le-Roy K. Shermen", "optd": "Robert E. Horten.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The theory of infiltration capacity was given by", "opta": "Merrill Bernard", "optb": "W.W. Horner", "optc": "Le-Roy K. Shermen", "optd": "Robert E. Horten.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Hydrology helps in", "opta": "predicting maximum flows", "optb": "deciding the minimum reservoir capacity", "optc": "forecasting the availability of quantity of water at reservoir site", "optd": "predicting the effects on the river water level on completion of dams", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following :", "opta": "Rivers, lakes, oceans and springs get water from the rains", "optb": "Rain water is obtained by evaporation from rivers, lakes and oceans", "optc": "Water remains in atmosphere as vapours", "optd": "Hydrologic cycle is a continuous process of evaporation and precipitation of water in atmosphere", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following :", "opta": "Rain which is intercepted by buildings, vegetations and other objects, is generally known as rainfall interception", "optb": "The difference between the total rainfall and intercepted rainfall, is generally called ground rainfall", "optc": "When rainfall exceeds the interception rainfall, water reaches the ground and infiltration starts", "optd": "The maximum rate of absorbing water by the soil in any given condition, is known as infiltration capacity", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The surface Run-off is the quantity of water", "opta": "absorbed by soil", "optb": "intercepted by buildings and vegetative cover", "optc": "required to fill surface depressions", "optd": "that reaches the stream channels", "opte": "that gets evaporated.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct equation from the following :", "opta": "Run off = Surface run off + Ground water flow", "optb": "Run off = Surface run off - Ground water flow", "optc": "Run off = Surface run off / Ground water flow", "optd": "Run off = Surface run off x Ground water flow.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Infiltration capacity of soil depends upon", "opta": "number of voids present in the soil", "optb": "shape and size of soil particles", "optc": "arrangement of soil particles", "optd": "compaction of the soil particles", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following :", "opta": "When rainfall rate exceeds the infiltration capacity, the water enters the soil at full capacity rate", "optb": "When rainfall rate is less than the infiltration capacity, the infiltration rate is approximately equal to the rainfall rate", "optc": "The actual infiltration rate at any time may be equal to or less than the infiltration capacity", "optd": "The actual prevailing rate of infiltration of water in the soil at any time, is known as infiltration rate", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following :", "opta": "The portion of pellicular water which remains unutilised, is called hygroscopic water", "optb": "The moisture content at which permanent wilting of plants takes place, is called the wilting point", "optc": "The path of the water required to bring the soil moisture content of a soil up to its field capacity is called soil moisture deficiency", "optd": "The moisture deficiency will be different at different points", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The main factor which affects the infiltration capacity, is", "opta": "thickness of saturated layer", "optb": "depth of surface detention", "optc": "soil moisture", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "According to Robert E. Horton, the equation of infiltration capacity curve, is (where letters carry their usual meanings)", "opta": "f = fc (fo - fc) ekt", "optb": "f = ft - (fo - fc) e-kt", "optc": "f = ft + (fo - fc) e-kt", "optd": "f = f + (fo - fc) ekt", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following :", "opta": "Absolute humidity at a given temperature is equal to weight of moisture present in a unit volume", "optb": "Relative humidity is the ratio of actual vapour pressure and saturation vapour pressure at the same temperature", "optc": "Relative humidity is the ratio of the weight of the vapours present per unit volume to the weight of vapours which could be contained at the same temperature when fully saturated", "optd": "Humidity can be measured by psychrometer", "opte": "All the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Absolute humidity in air", "opta": "decreases at higher altitudes", "optb": "increases at higher altitudes", "optc": "remains constant at all altitudes", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Precipitation caused by lifting of an air mass due to the pressure difference, is called", "opta": "cyclonic precipitation", "optb": "convective precipitation", "optc": "orographic precipitation", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The standard height of a standard rain gauge, is", "opta": "10 cm", "optb": "20 cm", "optc": "30 cm", "optd": "50 cm.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In India, rain fall is generally recorded at", "opta": "8 A.M.", "optb": "12 Noon", "optc": "4 P.M.", "optd": "8 P.M.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A recording type rain gauge", "opta": "produces a mass curve of rain fall", "optb": "records the cumulative rain", "optc": "is sometimes called integrating rain gauge or continuous rain gauge", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In India the recording type rain gauge generally used, is", "opta": "weighing type", "optb": "tipping type", "optc": "float recording type", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The deficiency in rain catch due to vertical acceleration of air forced upward over the gauge, is", "opta": "greater for heavy rain", "optb": "greater for lighter rain", "optc": "greater for large drops", "optd": "lesser for small rain drops.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If a gauge is installed perpendicular to the slope, its measurement is reduced by multiplying", "opta": "sine of the angle of inclination with vertical", "optb": "cosine of the angle of inclination with vertical", "optc": "tangent of the angle of inclination with vertical", "optd": "calibration coefficient of the gauge.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For determination of average annual precipitation in a catchment basin, the best method is", "opta": "Arithmetical method", "optb": "Thiessen's mean method", "optc": "Isohyetal method", "optd": "None of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "While calculating the average depth of annual precipitation in a catchment basin, importance to individual raingauge station is given in", "opta": "Arithmetical method", "optb": "Thiessen's mean method", "optc": "Isohyetal method", "optd": "both (a) and (b)", "opte": "both (b) and (c).", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The critical depth in a channel can be produced", "opta": "by raising the bottom of the channel", "optb": "by lowering the bottom of the channel", "optc": "by decreasing the width of the channel", "optd": "by increasing the width of the channel", "opte": "both (a) and (c) of above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A hydraulic jump in a control meter will be formed above the control, if its original", "opta": "depth is more than critical depth", "optb": "depth is less than the critical depth", "optc": "depth is equal to critical depth", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Prof. Running suggested the method for extending the discharge curve. It is known as", "opta": "Logarithmic method", "optb": "y method", "optc": "General method", "optd": "None of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If y is the depth of water at any section, then the mean velocity is", "opta": "0.1 y", "optb": "0.2 y", "optc": "0.3 y", "optd": "0.5 y", "opte": "0.6 y.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The run off is affected by", "opta": "type of precipitation", "optb": "rain intensity and duration of rainfall", "optc": "rain distribution and soil moisture deficiency", "optd": "direction of prevailing storm", "opte": "all the above.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The initial basin recharge is equal to", "opta": "interception", "optb": "depression storage", "optc": "rain absorbed by the moisture deficiency", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The run off a drainage basin is", "opta": "Initial recharge + ground water accretion + precipitation", "optb": "Precipitation + ground water accretion + initial recharge", "optc": "Precipitation - ground water accretion + initial recharge", "optd": "Precipitation - ground water accretion - initial recharge.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For computing the run off volumes of large areas, number of infiltrations used are", "opta": "2", "optb": "3", "optc": "4", "optd": "5", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "From the Survey of India map, the distance of the critical point is 20 km and difference in elevation is 193 m. The over land flow time, is", "opta": "2 hours", "optb": "3 hours", "optc": "2 hours and 30 minutes", "optd": "3 hours and 30 minutes", "opte": "4 hours.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If the area of storm hydrograph is equal to 102 cm, the ordinates of a unit hydrograph may be obtained by dividing the ordinates of the storm hydrograph by", "opta": "0.5", "optb": "1", "optc": "2", "optd": "3", "opte": "4", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If s is the potential infiltration, P is rainfall in cm in a drainage of a soil with fair pasture cover, the direct run off Q in cm is given by", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If the potential infiltration of a water shed having a soil with fair pasture cover, is 10 cm and rainfall is 12 cm, the direct run off is :", "opta": "2 cm", "optb": "3 cm", "optc": "5 cm", "optd": "8 cm.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The quantity of water retained by the sub-soil against gravity, is known", "opta": "yield", "optb": "porosity", "optc": "specific yield", "optd": "specific retention", "opte": "none of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the incorrect statement from the following :", "opta": "The rate of flow of water through a unit cross-sectional area under a unit hydraulic gradient, is called coefficient of permeability", "optb": "The rate of flow of water through a vertical strip of the acquifer of unit width and full depth under a unit hydraulic gradient, is called coefficient of transmissibility", "optc": "The flow of water through acquifers, is governed by the Darcy's law", "optd": "The term 'transmissibility' was introduced by Meinzer", "opte": "The ratio of coefficient of transmissibility and coefficient of permeability, is equal to the depth of acquifer through which water flows.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "With the usual meanings ofletters, the equation  is used for determining the velocity of ground water flow in metres per day. It is known as", "opta": "Meinzer's formula", "optb": "Slichter's formula", "optc": "Darcy's formula", "optd": "Hazen's formula.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If the viscosity of ground water is 1.00, the Slitcher's constant is 400, the effective size of soil particles in acquifer is 0.5 mm and hydraulic gradient is 1 in 80, the velocity of flow is", "opta": "0.25 m/day", "optb": "0.50 m/day", "optc": "0.75 m/day", "optd": "1.00 m/day", "opte": "1.25 m/day.", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following :", "opta": "Perched aquifer is found in unconfined aquifer", "optb": "The top surface of the water held in the perched aquifer, is known as perched water table", "optc": "Perched aquifer is formed in unfined accquifer if an impervious layer exists", "optd": "All the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In the derivation of Thiem's formula , the following assumption is not applicable", "opta": "The aquifer is homogeneous and isotropic", "optb": "Flow lines are radial and horizontal", "optc": "The slope of the water surface is too small", "optd": "The well has been sunk up to the surface of the unconfined aquifer", "opte": "None of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A well penetrates to 30 m below the static water table. After 24 hours of pumping at 31.40 litres/minute, the water level in a test well at a distance of 80 m is lowered by 0.5 m and in a well 20 m away water is lowered by 1.0 m. The transmissibility of the auifer, is", "opta": "1.185 m2/minute", "optb": "1.285 m2/minute", "optc": "1.385 m2/minute", "optd": "1.485 m2/minute", "opte": "1.585 m2/minute.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Shrouding is provided in", "opta": "cavity type tube wells", "optb": "slotted type tube wells", "optc": "strainer type tube wells", "optd": "perforated type tube wells.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The efficiency of a pump may be taken as", "opta": "0.55", "optb": "0.60", "optc": "0.65", "optd": "0.70", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Consumptive use of a crop during growth, is the amount of", "opta": "interception", "optb": "transpiration", "optc": "evaporation", "optd": "all the above.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For calculating the evaporation rate over a reservoir surface E = 0.771 (1.465 - 0.00732 B) (0.44 - 0.007375 V) (pe - pa), the equation is given by", "opta": "Roohwer's, formula in M.K.S.", "optb": "Roohwer's formula in F.P.S.", "optc": "Dalton's formula in F.P.S.", "optd": "Dalton's formula in M.K.S.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For the estimate of high floods in fan-shaped catchment, the formula used is", "opta": "Dicken's formula", "optb": "Ryve's formula", "optc": "Inglis formula", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Burge formula  cumecs is based upon", "opta": "rainfall and drainage area", "optb": "run off and drainage area", "optc": "drainage area and its shape", "optd": "drainage area.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}]]}